<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Aman King</title>
    <description>Aman King</description>
    <link>http://www.amanking.com</link>
    <pubDate>2014-07-27 19:53:32 +0530</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>3 Conferences in 3 Days</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/3-conferences-in-3-days</link>
      <pubDate>2014-07-27</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17-19 July 2014&lt;/strong&gt; were exciting days for me. On each of these days, I attended different conferences on different themes with different types of audiences. The only thing in common was that all of these were in Bangalore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;17 July:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/next-generation-testing-conference-2014"&gt;Next Generation Testing Conference&lt;/a&gt;, Le M&#xE9;ridien hotel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;18 July:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/jschannel-javascript-conference-2014"&gt;JSChannel JavaScript Conference&lt;/a&gt;, Taj Vivanta hotel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;em&gt;19 July:&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/sapientnitro-what-s-next-is-now-2014"&gt;SapientNitro What's Next is Now Conference&lt;/a&gt;, Marriott hotel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next Generation Testing was a 2-day conference. Fellow ThoughtWorker, Vatsala Singh, and I had submitted a talk which, fortunately, got scheduled for the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; day of the conference. This allowed me to attend the JSChannel conference the next day! Something I couldn't have missed as Douglas Crockford, possibly the biggest name in JavaScript circles was giving the opening keynote! JSChannel conference was also a 2-day event which I attended only for the first day. I had to skip the second day to attend SapientNitro's 1-day conference. It was important for me to attend that as I was personally invited by someone with whom I've enjoyed working in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through these conferences, I also got to experience the food and hospitality of three renowned hotels. I was impressed the most by Marriott, followed by Taj Vivanta, and finally Le M&#xE9;ridien.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure when I'll have such a whirlwind conference-attending experience again, but I will look forward to it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SapientNitro What's Next is Now 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/sapientnitro-what-s-next-is-now-2014</link>
      <pubDate>2014-07-26</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;19 July, Marriott hotel, Bangalore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="SapientNitro What's Next is Now 2014" src="http://www.amanking.com/assets/media/images/talks/SapientNitroConf2014.jpg" style="float:left; margin: 20px 20px 5px 0px; width: auto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invitation to &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/sapientnitro"&gt;SapientNitro&lt;/a&gt;'s 1-day conference was extended to me by someone with whom I had worked closely on a client-side consulting engagement. It was difficult to refuse, especially since the session topics seemed so interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The speakers were senior SapientNitro technologists who had recently completed a year-long &lt;a href="http://sapientnitroblog.com/post/92035552475"&gt;executive development programme&lt;/a&gt;. The attendees were mostly architects and senior technologists at SapientNitro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must admit that the quality of all the speakers' presentations was top-notch, including both visuals and content. There was also an impressive consistency across everyone's slides that made the sessions through the day seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the topics I enjoyed included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personalized Recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Physical Computing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modern Customer Loyalty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ad Space Evolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presentation Design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of parallel tracks, I had to miss other topics like Big Data, Content Marketing, Social Intelligence, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed all the sessions I attended, and had at least one question for every speaker. By the end of the day, everyone knew me as the person with a lot of questions. I was the only one representing &lt;a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com"&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt; there. I got to interact with multiple SapientNitro employees, old acquaintances and new, including their leadership team. They left a positive impression on me, and overall, it was a day well-spent. I am glad I attended.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JSChannel JavaScript Conference 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/jschannel-javascript-conference-2014</link>
      <pubDate>2014-07-25</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;18 July, Taj Vivanta hotel, Bangalore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Douglas Crockford at JSChannel Bangalore 2014" src="http://www.amanking.com/assets/media/images/talks/DouglasCrockfordJSChannel2014.jpg" style="float:right; margin: 0px 0px 10px 20px; width: auto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douglas. Crockford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need I say more?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly the most esteemed name in JavaScript, the person who gave us JSON, and all those &lt;a href="http://yuiblog.com/crockford/"&gt;JS lecture videos&lt;/a&gt;, and of course, the &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0596517742/wrrrldwideweb"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; that helped thousands gain a deeper understanding of the JavaScript language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.crockford.com/"&gt;Douglas Crockford&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; gave the opening keynote. He talked about the good parts of the latest work being done on &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ECMAScript"&gt;JavaScript evolution&lt;/a&gt;, and some parts that he did not like. He believes JavaScript continues to suffer because it tries to accommodate beginners while reality is that most of its users are not beginners. He also introduced &lt;a href="https://github.com/douglascrockford/DEC64"&gt;Dec64&lt;/a&gt; as a good option for a number data type. Douglas revisited &lt;a href="http://json.org/"&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; in the current context of communication protocols. Most useful of all, was his advise to developers using JavaScript, which could be summed up succinctly as &lt;em&gt;"Don't make bugs".&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Douglas was followed by &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/threepointone"&gt;Sunil Pai&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; from Myntra. Dressed in casual clothing, with harmless sarcastic wit, and a great sense of humour, Sunil had an effective way of presenting. He came off as relatable, passionate, and as someone who enjoys doing what he does. There is definitely some interesting work going on in Myntra, involving &lt;a href="http://nodejs.org/"&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt;, re-architecting, and building a scalable product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fellow ThoughtWorker, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/suchitpuri"&gt;Suchit Puri&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/strong&gt; presented some of his team's learnings involving &lt;a href="http://emberjs.com/"&gt;EmberJS&lt;/a&gt;. By the look of it, the framework seems opinionated, inspired from Rails, and solves multiple use cases in the client-side MVC domain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the two parallel workshop tracks, I attended &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/kmanchanda"&gt;Kapil Manchanda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;'s HTML5 Game Programming workshop. It was fun seeing a simple but fun game getting built from scratch, using &lt;a href="http://phaser.io/"&gt;phaser.io&lt;/a&gt;. I definitely got some starting insights. Perhaps I'll be able to take time off to build a game of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day 1 wrapped up with some lightning talks, and networking over tea. Besides a few new acquaintances, I caught up with multiple ThoughtWorkers and ex-ThoughtWorkers, and some people from a previous client-side assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, &lt;a href="http://www.jschannel.com/"&gt;JSChannel&lt;/a&gt; continues to be a good conference, worth attending. I would have loved to attend Day 2 but had to attend a &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/sapientnitro-what-s-next-is-now-2014"&gt;SapientNitro conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next Generation Testing Conference 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/next-generation-testing-conference-2014</link>
      <pubDate>2014-07-24</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;17 July, Le M&#xE9;ridien hotel, Bangalore&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="http://www.nextgentesting.org/bangalore/2014/World_Conference_Testing/program"&gt;conference&lt;/a&gt; presented by &lt;a href="https://www.facebook.com/joinunicom"&gt;Unicom Learning&lt;/a&gt;, it was attended by over 350 professionals. Interesting topics were covered by 34 speakers in all. The speakers included my colleague, &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/anandbagmar"&gt;Anand Bagmar&lt;/a&gt;, and myself. &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/vatsala-singh/1/644/b82"&gt;Vatsala Singh&lt;/a&gt;, my co-speaker and fellow ThoughtWorker, could not make it on that day due to work reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favourite talks from Day 1 were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://onedrive.live.com/view.aspx?resid=C1C07DFE86ED215E!477&amp;amp;ithint=file%2c.pdf&amp;amp;app=WordPdf&amp;amp;authkey=!ALp9b_tounqL1Co"&gt;Thinking like a Hacker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/santhosh-tuppad/12/b74/338"&gt;Santhosh Shivanand Tuppad&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://onedrive.live.com/view.aspx?resid=C1C07DFE86ED215E!475&amp;amp;ithint=file%2c.pdf&amp;amp;app=WordPdf&amp;amp;authkey=!ABYG6ZzXvRHiw2U"&gt;Enabling Continuous Delivery in Enterprises with Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/in/anandbagmar"&gt;Anand Bagmar&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://onedrive.live.com/view.aspx?resid=C1C07DFE86ED215E!465&amp;amp;ithint=file%2c.pdf&amp;amp;app=WordPdf&amp;amp;authkey=!AGB6l2FB57h2BYk"&gt;Transforming Software Testing Through Managed Crowdsourcing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; by &lt;a href="http://www.linkedin.com/pub/mayank-mittal/11/894/a66"&gt;Mayank Mittal&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Santhosh's talk was refreshingly different. His take on various aspects, including personal relationships, sources of motivation, morality, ways to learn, were unique to him. The candour and humour in his presentation style was impressive. He had everyone laughing through most of his talk. In Q&amp;amp;A, one person asked how this talk was tied to testing. While not explicit, I think most people had gotten the underlying intent: &lt;em&gt;"Set a thief to catch a thief",&lt;/em&gt; ie, to be effective in Security Testing, one needs to learn how to bypass security measures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand's talk was a great introduction to some Agile practices that help teams move towards Continuous Delivery. He extrapolated those in an enterprise context, and shared ideas on how to adapt these practices with scale. While most ThoughtWorkers would identify with the concepts already, as these are ingrained in our daily work, the key message of &lt;em&gt;"A Triangle = A Pentagon"&lt;/em&gt; is not something that strikes us naturally, and was definitely novel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mayank exposed the audience to a new way of executing testing activity by using &lt;em&gt;crowdsourcing.&lt;/em&gt; He covered the benefits of such an approach and how to go about it. While a simplified breakdown helped us understand the model, during Q&amp;amp;A, Mayank touched upon the hidden complexities as well. This is definitely something to keep an eye on, and perhaps leverage under appropriate circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Aman King at Next Gen Testing 2014" src="http://www.amanking.com/assets/media/images/talks/NextGenTesting2014.JPG" style="float:left; margin: 10px 20px 5px 0px; width: auto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made many new connections in the conference. The talk I delivered helped the audience relate with a number of Agile Testing Dilemmas that Vatsala and I incorporated into the presentation. People approached me after the talk, and we engaged in interesting conversations related to their current situations. I felt there were many who had embarked on an Agile journey in their organizations but could use further guidance. There are also misinterpretations and misimplementations to be wary of. They could benefit from some sort of &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile Coaching&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would have loved to attend Day 2 but had to attend the &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/jschannel-javascript-conference-2014"&gt;JSChannel JavaScript conference&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the slides that Vatsala and I had prepared for the conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/37090007?rel=0" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:1px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/amanking/agile-testing-dilemmas" title="Agile Testing Dilemmas" target="_blank"&gt;Agile Testing Dilemmas&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/amanking" target="_blank"&gt;Aman King&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile India 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/agile-india-2014</link>
      <pubDate>2014-03-14</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spoke at &lt;a href="http://2014.agileindia.org/"&gt;Agile India 2014&lt;/a&gt; on 26 Feb for the &lt;em&gt;Scaling Agile Adoption&lt;/em&gt; theme. I also attended the &lt;em&gt;Beyond Agile&lt;/em&gt; theme. As cited &lt;a href="http://blog.agileindia.org/2014/03/04/agile-india-2014-conference-final-attendees-profile/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, the conference attracted 1236 attendees from 28 different countries across 200+ different companies. It was among the largest Agile conferences in Asia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people connected with me after my talk: &lt;a href="http://present.agileindia.org/proposal/16/from-practitioner-to-coach"&gt;From Practitioner to Coach&lt;/a&gt;. I gained context on various organizations and their Agile-related initiatives. Met a good number of first-time coaches as well. If you're interested in the topic, you may find my &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/publications"&gt;experience report&lt;/a&gt; worth a read. I've also blogged on &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/tags#coaching-ref"&gt;coaching topics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feedback about my talk that I will treasure the most came from &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Lyssa-Adkins/e/B003ED6OQY"&gt;Lyssa Adkins&lt;/a&gt;, author of &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Coaching-Agile-Teams-ScrumMasters-Addison-Wesley-ebook/dp/B003QP47YG/"&gt;Coaching Agile Teams&lt;/a&gt; and co-founder of &lt;a href="http://www.agilecoachinginstitute.com/"&gt;Agile Coaching Institute&lt;/a&gt;. This is what she tweeted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="From Practitioner to Coach - tweet from Lyssa Adkins" src="http://www.amanking.com/assets/media/images/talks/LyssaAdkinsTwitterReaction.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
As an attendee, here are my reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Scaling Agile Adoption day, I enjoyed Martin Fowler's keynote, especially the part about &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/articles/agileFluency.html"&gt;Agile Fluency&lt;/a&gt;. I started to attend Colin's tutorial on &lt;a href="http://present.agileindia.org/proposal/185/achieving-enterprise-agility-with-the-scaled-agile-frameworkand-have-fun-doing-it"&gt;Scaled Agile Framework&lt;/a&gt; as I've had mixed experiences with it in client organizations. However, since the talk started by spending time on Agile basics, I applied the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_Space_Technology#Law_of_two_feet"&gt;law of two feet&lt;/a&gt; and attended Lyssa and Michael's talk on &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/31394807"&gt;Windows on Transformation&lt;/a&gt;. I identified with the content well, given my consulting/coaching experience, and enjoyed the talk. The day ended with a moving presentation by Rae on &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/31711674"&gt;Engendering Justice: Women, War and Peace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Beyond Agile day, Dave Thomas hit upon the topic of &lt;a href="http://pragdave.me/blog/2014/03/04/time-to-kill-agile/"&gt;Agility vs Agile&lt;/a&gt; in his keynote. Tathagat Varma set the foundation well for his talk on &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/Managewell/what-next-31791295"&gt;Management 3.0 and Holacracy&lt;/a&gt; but I switched in between to attend my ex-colleague Nikhil Joshi's talk on &lt;a href="http://prezi.com/uuknbj2lfddl/build-measure-learn-without-spending-a-fortune/"&gt;Build-Measure-Learn&lt;/a&gt;. Nikhil was able to establish how you can have a Minimal Viable Product without writing even a single line of code! Lyssa and Michael shared a dead-simple &lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/31396601"&gt;competency framework&lt;/a&gt; for Agile Coaching, which could be used to great effect. Finally I enjoyed Venkat's no-pretence talk about his &lt;a href="http://present.agileindia.org/proposal/248/applying-agile-to-a-bootstrapped-startup"&gt;startup journey&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="https://apartmentadda.com"&gt;ApartmentADDA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I enjoyed some of the talks and learnt a few things. Also networked with a variety of people. The food was good too. That said, as natural to expect, some speakers could have had better delivery style, more focus on content, and attention toward slide readability. Speakers need to start following &lt;a href="http://www.amanking.com/tips-for-technical-conference-presentations"&gt;simple tips&lt;/a&gt; to improve their slides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All said and done, I am grateful for the speaking opportunity I got. Enabled me to pass on a message that I feel could help others. I definitely look forward to Agile India 2015!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/31713572?rel=0" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px 1px 0; margin-bottom:1px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;div style="margin-bottom:5px"&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.slideshare.net/amanking/from-practitioner-to-coach" title="From Practitioner to Coach" target="_blank"&gt;From Practitioner to Coach&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/amanking" target="_blank"&gt;Aman King&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
