<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Aman King</title>
    <link>http://www.amanking.com</link>
    <pubDate>2013-12-20 02:18:39 +0530</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>Self-discovery</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/self-discovery</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-19</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Self-discovery&lt;/em&gt; is important for an individual to understand oneself better, and to continuously grow or evolve. While important for one&amp;#39;s personal life, it is also applicable to one&amp;#39;s professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="/coaching-basics"&gt;coaching&lt;/a&gt;, one of the goals is to aid individuals to gain better awareness of their own potential. While one way to address this is to provide continuous feedback, it additionally helps if individuals are enabled to learn more about themselves on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some tools that I have personally found useful and have recommended to others:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://strengths.gallup.com/110440/About-StrengthsFinder-20.aspx"&gt;Strengths Finder&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mindtimemaps.com/"&gt;MindTimeMaps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other activity-based suggestions include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.noop.nl/2011/09/moving-motivators-free-exercise.html"&gt;Moving Motivators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.jthoenes.net/personal-retrospectives/"&gt;Personal Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you take online questionnaires, conduct introspective exercises or retrospectives, or simply reflect on feedback received, it is useful to take some time out to think about yourself and your place in the surrounding context. Having gone through certain experiences and learnings, reflecting on those and imbibing key takeaways will ensure that you grow in the process. Else there is a risk that each incident, whether good or bad, remains just as an incident in your memory, and does not become an opportunity to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discovery in individuals, combined with &lt;a href="/self-learning"&gt;self-learning&lt;/a&gt;, is key to sustenance, especially in Agile Coaching.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-learning</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/self-learning</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-18</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A good degree of &lt;em&gt;self-learning&lt;/em&gt; is expected out of every individual being coached during an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile Adoption&lt;/a&gt;. Without it, individuals cannot move through the various stages of learning as put across by the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dreyfus_model_of_skill_acquisition"&gt;Dreyfus Model&lt;/a&gt;. An Agile Coach may pair on tasks with individuals but such an approach is limited by team size, and one-on-one attention cannot be given for extended durations of time. After all, the way an Agile Coach operates is different from that of a Personal Trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Agile Coach will usually focus on providing the building blocks, and then set the individual on the path of self-learning. This is the approach right from the onset, where instead of spoon-feeding answers, the coach will use effective questioning to guide the individual to come up with their own reasonable conclusions. This is an application of what is widely known as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socratic_method"&gt;Socratic Method&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally what I follow is the &lt;a href="http://www.princeton.edu/hr/learning/philosophy/"&gt;Princeton Model&lt;/a&gt; of learning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Princeton Model" src="/assets/media/images/coaching/princeton-model.png" style="float:right; margin: 0px 0px 0px 20px; width: auto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;70%&lt;/em&gt; of the skills adoption comes from real work done on the ground. I pair with individuals on actual project work, and have coached individuals pair with others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;20%&lt;/em&gt; of the skills adoption happens via workshops, sessions, and demos. These workshops are conducted by me or other invited experts. Demos and knowledge-sharing brown bag sessions are conducted on a regular basis within the team, where team members themselves volunteer to show-and-tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;10%&lt;/em&gt; of skills exposure happens via reading. Links to relevant articles and blogs are shared via mailing lists or wiki pages. Book recommendations are also made, and possibly added to a library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I have also seen encourage self-learning in teams is to throw challenges at them, and see them cope with it by upgrading their skill levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Challenges vs Skills" src="/assets/media/images/coaching/challenges-vs-skills.png" style="float:left; margin: 0px 20px 20px 0px; width: auto"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an individual is dealing with challenges which are underwhelming, and do not require full utilization of existing skills, the individual gets bored or complacent. If, however, the individual is put up with overwhelming challenges, the individual will experience some frustration or stress, and will either try to reduce the challenges or will learn skills appropriate to overcome the challenges. If steered toward the latter behavior, the person grows in competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style="clear:both"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the ways in which self-learning can take place in individuals and teams. They are effective tools to use during active coaching, to make a team reach levels of sustenance. This process may lead some individuals down the path to &lt;a href="/self-discovery"&gt;self-discovery&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring Progress</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/measuring-progress</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-17</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;If you can not measure it, you can not improve it.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Thomson,_1st_Baron_Kelvin"&gt;Lord Kelvin&lt;/a&gt; is accredited with the above quote. He was not talking about Agile software development but he was probably on to &lt;em&gt;continuous improvement&lt;/em&gt;. The latter is &lt;a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/principles.html"&gt;integral&lt;/a&gt; to the former.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A positive change on a metric can be an &lt;em&gt;indicator&lt;/em&gt; of progress or improvement. It is not a guarantee of progress but an indicator. Perhaps if we combine different metrics, all indicating progress on interconnected concepts, we can have higher confidence that there is improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Sample Case Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us say Team A and Team B both start off with 2% code coverage. There is strong &lt;em&gt;encouragement&lt;/em&gt; from Management that coverage needs to improve. Team A adopts a traditional unit testing approach, ie, adding tests after code is written. Team B adopts TDD, ie, writing test first and then code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months later, Team A has 25% code coverage. Team B has 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which team has made better progress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer is we don&amp;#39;t know. If we treat &lt;em&gt;measuring progress&lt;/em&gt; as equivalent to &lt;em&gt;measuring code coverage&lt;/em&gt;, clearly Team A is better off. But is progress the same as code coverage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us bring in another metric: Avg Defect Count per Iteration. Let&amp;#39;s say Team A and B both started with 20. After the two months, Team A has a defect count of 12, while Team B has 8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="1"&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Team&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Coverage - Before&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Avg Defect Count - Before&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Coverage - After&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Avg Defect Count - After&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;A&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;25%&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;B&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;2%&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;10%&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Which team has made better progress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these combined metrics, we are tempted to say Team B. Because having lesser defects seems associated with quality improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps for Team B, TDD led to better understanding of new features and improved quality. However, it did not increase code coverage for existing code that was not touched. On the other hand, Team A focused on increasing code coverage but the effectiveness of the covering tests was questionable, which resulted in higher coverage but not a proportional gain in quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, our answer could still be wrong! Perhaps Team B had a couple of QAs go on vacation, which led to some stories not being tested exhaustively (functional, manual, exploratory, etc), and hence, lesser defects were found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The learning is that these numbers are all indicators, and subjectivity has to be applied. Measuring progress is not about measuring numbers. Continuous improvement is not about improving numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having established that, indicators are still necessary and can be an asset during &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-roles"&gt;Agile Coaching&lt;/a&gt;. If we feel the team is making progress, an improvement in numbers will support that. Corollary is that if numbers show a downward trend, we need to investigate if there are slippages or reasonable circumstances to account for that. For all the following suggestions, what is useful is tracking them over a period of time. Based on context, you could decided how frequently to capture them, and how to analyze the results, and if any action item is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_2"&gt;Metrics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metrics used for &lt;em&gt;baselining&lt;/em&gt; can be used for continuous monitoring. Remember to choose metrics based on goals, and definitely choose more than one. You can read more &lt;a href="/metrics-baselining"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_3"&gt;Confidence Meter&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another technique I have seen used effectively is a &lt;em&gt;Confidence Meter&lt;/em&gt;. On or near the Story Wall, we could have a flipchart or whiteboard area to capture the confidence which individual team members have in making a successful release at the end of the iteration. 90% or higher reflects great confidence while anything lower than 30% shows lack of confidence. Team members could update these numbers against their name at the end of a stand up, and if there is a wide variance in perspectives, it could trigger discussions immediately instead of waiting till a Retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_4"&gt;Surveys&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One technique, strong on subjectivity, is &lt;em&gt;Surveys&lt;/em&gt;. It may seem casual and imprecise but the results can be revealing. A good survey will have a mix of objective and subjective questions. An objective question could be &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Has frequency and pace of refactoring increased?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;, with options ranging from &lt;em&gt;0 (Barely)&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;5 (Great extent)&lt;/em&gt;. A subjective comment box could capture something like &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Do you feel confident to help others with XP Practices, and in what areas?&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
You can come up with more things to track to indicate progress in your team&amp;#39;s context. It also helps motivation if you can make the trend visible, perhaps by using Big Visible Charts or Information Radiators. But yes, ever so often, do check and remind people that the goal is to make progress and to improve on aspects that provide value to the Business or end users, and not to get solely number-driven.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facilitation Techniques</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/facilitation-techniques</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-16</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Facilitation is a very useful skill to have. It helps not only in &lt;a href="/coaching-basics"&gt;coaching&lt;/a&gt; but in many day-to-day activities. Whether a team discussion or a team activity, a good facilitator can make all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_0"&gt;Retrospective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common facilitation technique is a &lt;em&gt;Retrospective&lt;/em&gt;. It has a clear objective of looking back, as a group, at a recent time period or a particular incident, collect thoughts around different aspects, and then brainstorm on action items related to the topic. Agile teams use this technique for continuous improvement. I like relating it to &lt;a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/principles.html"&gt;the 12th Agile Principle&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;At regular intervals, the team reflects on how to become more effective, then tunes and adjusts its behavior accordingly.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are some well-known Retrospective formats, I try to customize the experience based on context. This could be how the recent iteration went, the motivation levels of the team, concepts that the team can relate to, or sometimes just something random that could be fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="Retro" src="/assets/media/images/coaching/retro.png"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;small class="muted"&gt;Retro using a Fuel/Mud analogy&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_1"&gt;Future-spective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variation of the Retrospective is a &lt;em&gt;Future-spective&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, it is not about looking back but about looking forward. Such an exercise helps in goal-setting, expectation-setting, coming up with a common vision, and sometimes an actionable plan. Typically it involves having the group imagine that they are in the future, and then describing what they see has gone well or what has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_2"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lesser used technique for facilitation is &lt;em&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/em&gt;. A number of people have discovered it for personal use. I have used it in group situations as well, whether to make my own thoughts visual so that others can follow or to capture thoughts of the group, presenting it back to them in real time. Having thoughts captured visually and linked together, helps explore the topic space even further, and make stronger connections between different ideas. It also helps retention. Mind Mapping can be used effectively for cause-effect analysis or for drilling down a concept into granular levels which are more easily recognizable or actionable. In fact, you could use this technique in a Retrospective to draw out effective action items after points have been put forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_3"&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you may be facilitating a large group, or a group that isn&amp;#39;t very vocal, or perhaps a topic that is a bit controversial. In all of these cases, having an effective discussion may be difficult. Here a technique called as &lt;em&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/em&gt; can help. It is a constrained form of discussion where there are set rules for participation. At any given point in time, there is a panel with a fixed number of chairs. Out of these chairs, all but one can be filled by people who wish to participate in the discussion. If someone new steps in and sits on the vacant chair, one of the other participants has to volunteer to step out. This encourages multiple viewpoints to be heard, and discourages anyone from overtaking the discussion for long. With groups that are not vocal, having many chairs empty creates an awkward situation, forcing a few people to self-nominate themselves for the panel discussion. Seeing a few people start off, others feel encouraged to join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
There are even more facilitation techniques that one can employ, for example, &lt;em&gt;fist of five&lt;/em&gt;. It is good to have them in your toolkit especially if you are in a role that could benefit from a collaborative team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_4"&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_5"&gt;Retrospectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/"&gt;Fun Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://retrospectivewiki.org/"&gt;Retrospectives Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives"&gt;Agile Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/the-retrospective-handbook"&gt;The Retrospective Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_6"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind_map"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://freemind.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Main_Page"&gt;FreeMind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mindmup.com/"&gt;MindMup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_7"&gt;General&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fishbowl_(conversation)"&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://java.dzone.com/articles/fist-five"&gt;Fist of five&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secrets-Facilitation-S-M-R-T-Getting/dp/0787975788"&gt;The Secrets of Facilitation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrics Baselining</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/metrics-baselining</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-15</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the assessment period of an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile coaching engagement&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of information is captured around the team&amp;#39;s &lt;a href="/process-mapping"&gt;current processes and practices&lt;/a&gt;. Along with these, gathering quantitative data is also important. These will go into the assessment report at the end, portraying some aspects of current state. Collecting such metrics during assessment is called &lt;em&gt;Metrics Baselining&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendations can be made on the basis of numbers and trends observed, especially using complementary metrics. If the assessment is followed by Agile Adoption, these metrics can be used to indicate progress in chosen areas. From a sustenance point of view, a Before/After comparison around these metrics can determine comfort level and for demonstrating coaching effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may think capturing quantitative data will be simpler than gathering qualitative data. In my experience, the former is trickier and even risky. From a tooling perspective, getting to the numbers might be easy enough. But knowing what numbers actually matter is where the complexity lies. Especially since typically during an assessment, the team and the coach themselves are unaware of exactly where the team&amp;#39;s challenges lie, and the assessment is supposed to help discover these. Tracking irrelevant metrics may send a team down a useless path, or worse, a harmful path. Metrics selection should be guided by clear meaningful goals. But when unsure, an Agile Coach may choose to capture whatever can be captured, with a clear disclaimer that it&amp;#39;s being done so that the information is available &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; it becomes useful later. So be sure to archive these metrics somewhere safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some typical metrics captured are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Productivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycle time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say/Do ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Velocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Quality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defect count over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defect ratio across environments or testing stages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Code base&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cyclomatic complexity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code toxicity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Build and deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build pass/fail ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on where the team is with certain practices, some of the above metrics may not be readily available or even applicable at the time of assessment. You may need to tweak what kind of metrics you gather in such cases by finding reasonable context-based alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot overstate how important it is to not become metrics-driven at this stage or even later. It is likely that the client may need to be educated around the perils of the same. A good guide may be the Goal-Question-Metric model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_4"&gt;Further resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_5"&gt;Metrics related&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.leadingagile.com/2013/07/agile-health-metrics-for-predictability/"&gt;Agile Health Metrics for Predictability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GQM"&gt;Goal-Question-Metric model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_6"&gt;Tools related&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycle time: &lt;a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/get-better-2-minutes-mingle-cycle-time-analytics"&gt;Mingle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://confluence.atlassian.com/display/AGILE/Viewing+the+Control+Chart"&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code metrics: &lt;a href="http://erik.doernenburg.com/2008/11/how-toxic-is-your-code/"&gt;Code Toxicity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Checkstyle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.sonarqube.org/"&gt;Sonar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
