<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Aman King</title>
    <link>http://www.amanking.com</link>
    <pubDate>2013-12-17 23:18:29 +0530</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>Facilitation Techniques</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/facilitation-techniques</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-16</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Facilitation is a very useful skill to have. It helps not only in &lt;a href="/coaching-basics"&gt;coaching&lt;/a&gt; but in many day-to-day activities. Whether a team discussion or a team activity, a good facilitator can make all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_0"&gt;Retrospective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common facilitation technique is a &lt;em&gt;Retrospective&lt;/em&gt;. It has a clear objective of looking back, as a group, at a recent time period or a particular incident, collect thoughts around different aspects, and then brainstorm on action items related to the topic. Agile teams use this technique for continuous improvement. I like relating it to &lt;a href="http://agilemanifesto.org/principles.html"&gt;the 12th Agile Principle&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;At regular intervals, the team reflects on how to become more effective, then tunes and adjusts its behavior accordingly.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there are some well-known Retrospective formats, I try to customize the experience based on context. This could be how the recent iteration went, the motivation levels of the team, concepts that the team can relate to, or sometimes just something random that could be fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="Retro" src="/assets/media/images/coaching/retro.png"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;small class="muted"&gt;Retro using a Fuel/Mud analogy&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_1"&gt;Future-spective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A variation of the Retrospective is a &lt;em&gt;Future-spective&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, it is not about looking back but about looking forward. Such an exercise helps in goal-setting, expectation-setting, coming up with a common vision, and sometimes an actionable plan. Typically it involves having the group imagine that they are in the future, and then describing what they see has gone well or what has gone wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_2"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lesser used technique for facilitation is &lt;em&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/em&gt;. A number of people have discovered it for personal use. I have used it in group situations as well, whether to make my own thoughts visual so that others can follow or to capture thoughts of the group, presenting it back to them in real time. Having thoughts captured visually and linked together, helps explore the topic space even further, and make stronger connections between different ideas. It also helps retention. Mind Mapping can be used effectively for cause-effect analysis or for drilling down a concept into granular levels which are more easily recognizable or actionable. In fact, you could use this technique in a Retrospective to draw out effective action items after points have been put forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_3"&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you may be facilitating a large group, or a group that isn&amp;#39;t very vocal, or perhaps a topic that is a bit controversial. In all of these cases, having an effective discussion may be difficult. Here a technique called as &lt;em&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/em&gt; can help. It is a constrained form of discussion where there are set rules for participation. At any given point in time, there is a panel with a fixed number of chairs. Out of these chairs, all but one can be filled by people who wish to participate in the discussion. If someone new steps in and sits on the vacant chair, one of the other participants has to volunteer to step out. This encourages multiple viewpoints to be heard, and discourages anyone from overtaking the discussion for long. With groups that are not vocal, having many chairs empty creates an awkward situation, forcing a few people to self-nominate themselves for the panel discussion. Seeing a few people start off, others feel encouraged to join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
There are even more facilitation techniques that one can employ, for example, &lt;em&gt;fist of five&lt;/em&gt;. It is good to have them in your toolkit especially if you are in a role that could benefit from a collaborative team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="toc_4"&gt;Further Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_5"&gt;Retrospectives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.funretrospectives.com/"&gt;Fun Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://retrospectivewiki.org/"&gt;Retrospectives Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pragprog.com/book/dlret/agile-retrospectives"&gt;Agile Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/the-retrospective-handbook"&gt;The Retrospective Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_6"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mind_map"&gt;Mind Mapping&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://freemind.sourceforge.net/wiki/index.php/Main_Page"&gt;FreeMind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mindmup.com/"&gt;MindMup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_7"&gt;General&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fishbowl_(conversation)"&gt;Fishbowl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://java.dzone.com/articles/fist-five"&gt;Fist of five&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Secrets-Facilitation-S-M-R-T-Getting/dp/0787975788"&gt;The Secrets of Facilitation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metrics Baselining</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/metrics-baselining</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-15</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the assessment period of an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile coaching engagement&lt;/a&gt;, a lot of information is captured around the team&amp;#39;s &lt;a href="/process-mapping"&gt;current processes and practices&lt;/a&gt;. Along with these, gathering quantitative data is also important. These will go into the assessment report at the end, portraying some aspects of current state. Collecting such metrics during assessment is called &lt;em&gt;Metrics Baselining&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommendations can be made on the basis of numbers and trends observed, especially using complementary metrics. If the assessment is followed by Agile Adoption, these metrics can be used to indicate progress in chosen areas. From a sustenance point of view, a Before/After comparison around these metrics can determine comfort level and for demonstrating coaching effectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may think capturing quantitative data will be simpler than gathering qualitative data. In my experience, the former is trickier and even risky. From a tooling perspective, getting to the numbers might be easy enough. But knowing what numbers actually matter is where the complexity lies. Especially since typically during an assessment, the team and the coach themselves are unaware of exactly where the team&amp;#39;s challenges lie, and the assessment is supposed to help discover these. Tracking irrelevant metrics may send a team down a useless path, or worse, a harmful path. Metrics selection should be guided by clear meaningful goals. But when unsure, an Agile Coach may choose to capture whatever can be captured, with a clear disclaimer that it&amp;#39;s being done so that the information is available &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; it becomes useful later. So be sure to archive these metrics somewhere safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some typical metrics captured are as follows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Productivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycle time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say/Do ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Velocity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Quality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defect count over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defect ratio across environments or testing stages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Code base&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cyclomatic complexity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code toxicity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Build and deployment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build pass/fail ratio&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on where the team is with certain practices, some of the above metrics may not be readily available or even applicable at the time of assessment. You may need to tweak what kind of metrics you gather in such cases by finding reasonable context-based alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot overstate how important it is to not become metrics-driven at this stage or even later. It is likely that the client may need to be educated around the perils of the same. A good guide may be the Goal-Question-Metric model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_4"&gt;Further resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_5"&gt;Metrics related&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.leadingagile.com/2013/07/agile-health-metrics-for-predictability/"&gt;Agile Health Metrics for Predictability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GQM"&gt;Goal-Question-Metric model&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id="toc_6"&gt;Tools related&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycle time: &lt;a href="http://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/blog/get-better-2-minutes-mingle-cycle-time-analytics"&gt;Mingle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://confluence.atlassian.com/display/AGILE/Viewing+the+Control+Chart"&gt;JIRA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Code metrics: &lt;a href="http://erik.doernenburg.com/2008/11/how-toxic-is-your-code/"&gt;Code Toxicity&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net/"&gt;Checkstyle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.sonarqube.org/"&gt;Sonar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Process Mapping</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/process-mapping</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-14</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After having collected enough information during the assessment period of an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile coaching engagement&lt;/a&gt;, especially using &lt;a href="/assessment-interviews"&gt;interviews&lt;/a&gt;, an Agile Coach should be in a position to draw a &lt;em&gt;Process Map&lt;/em&gt; of whatever has been discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could go use a tool to build a clean and elaborate process map but I recommend starting with stickies. Take a bunch of stickies and write down the important activities that you know different roles get involved in during the start of an iteration, at the end of an iteration, and in-between. Give a short name for the activity and note the name of the role as well. Keep the granularity at medium level, as you don&amp;#39;t want too many stickies at once, at least not initially.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now on a whiteboard, sequence these stickies, one at a time, in the order they are done. Draw connecting lines between the stickies as you proceed. If some activities are repeated, draw loops accordingly. You will now have a visual timeline of an iteration. If you can spot obvious gaps in the timeline, add more stickies for those missing activities along with role participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you will want to know more about what feeds into an iteration and how, and what goes out of an iteration and how. The former is usually around requirements and defect management. The latter is typically about releases and deployments. In most organizations, customer feedback and customer support connects the end point to the starting point. However, some of this could be just your assumption. It is unlikely you&amp;#39;d have gotten a complete view of the process as some of these aspects are not apparent mid-release nor are all team members aware of them. It is time to get proper validation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a pic of the process map you&amp;#39;ve come up with, and take it off the board. Keep the stickies handy though. Schedule an hour-long meeting with those roles who&amp;#39;d be aware of these steps at a high level. Typically it is a Project Manager, a Tech Lead, or the Product Owner. Repeat the above process in front of them (using your earlier stickies) but clearly call out every addition you make to the process map. Give them a chance to react at every step, getting either validation or corrections from them. Annotate the flow or the stickies themselves with any details you get. For the gaps or the big picture (before/after iteration), let them call out the activities and the roles involved (you could capture exact names of people as well). Cross-check with what you&amp;#39;d assumed. For those that match, use your stickies. For those that don&amp;#39;t, tear off your sticky and create new ones on the fly. In the end, summarize the map on the board to catch any obvious misses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="Process Map" src="/assets/media/images/coaching/process-map.png"&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;small class="muted"&gt;Sample process map&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep the map on the board, and show it to team members you had interviewed before. Get their insights about the visual. Mostly it should be a confirmation of the activities depicted. You could also get more details around certain activities. Additionally, you can cross-check different people&amp;#39;s viewpoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to capture this map using a tool or in the simplest case, attach a picture of it on a wiki page that describes the process in words as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have a process map, you could consider doing a &lt;em&gt;value stream mapping&lt;/em&gt; if you feel it will help with the engagement objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some related links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.isixsigma.com/tools-templates/process-mapping/building-valuable-process-maps-takes-skill-and-time/"&gt;Building process maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_stream_mapping"&gt;Value stream mapping - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/michael.sahota/value-stream-mapping-workshop"&gt;Value stream mapping workshop slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Assessment Interviews</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/assessment-interviews</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-13</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the assessment week of an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile coaching engagement&lt;/a&gt;, the goal is to learn about the current state of the team. Special attention is needed towards capturing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day-to-day activities of various roles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional activities such as on planning day, deployment day, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools used to support these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processes around these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interaction, collaboration, and dependency on other roles or teams during these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infrastructure environments involved in these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome of these activities in an iteration-level view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges faced in performing any of these activities or the role in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to remain objective while making observations, and to not fall into the temptation of drawing conclusions or making recommendations. The latter is needed but should come towards the end of the assessment when holistic information is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to get visibility into the above aspects is conducting interviews of team members. We need not talk to everyone but only a representative sample (perhaps 1-2 individuals) from each role. This should be complemented with first-hand observation of how they work. Here is a suggestion of how you could go about this activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Interview preparation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inform the Project Manager or equivalent a day or two in advance about the interviews you are planning to do. Learn about the various roles in the team, and ask the PM to inform team members to make time for the interview, which could last anywhere between 30 mins to an hour. It is usually a good idea to not conduct the interviews in a meeting room but at the desk of the individual. You should set up a time beforehand so that the interviewee is not distracted during the interview. Based on any insights already shared with you about the team&amp;#39;s current context, make a list of areas you want to specifically ask about. Some of these will be role-specific, and some general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Interview kickoff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduce or re-introduce yourself to the individual. Briefly let them know why you are there with the team. Explain what the interview is about and how it will help. The interviewee should not feel like this is a test which has right or wrong answers. Thank the person for agreeing to the interview. Try to keep the interaction balanced between formal and informal so that it seems important and yet the interviewee feels comfortable in opening up and being forthright. Keep a notebook handy, and inform the interviewee that you&amp;#39;ll be scribbling notes during the interview, which you can share later after some clean-up if the interviewee is interested. It helps to reinforce transparency. First thing to note down is the person&amp;#39;s name and role, along with the interview date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Interview questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start simple by asking about the person&amp;#39;s background in brief, typically around industry experience, how long with the current team, and role description. Follow this up by asking the person to describe their &lt;em&gt;typical day&lt;/em&gt;. You can expect to get a lot of information out of this. Be ready to probe for details as and when required. Don&amp;#39;t stick to going breadth-wise or depth-wise; switch how you elicit details based on how relevant you feel a topic is. You can even ask the individual to &lt;em&gt;show-and-tell&lt;/em&gt; some aspects, perhaps by using a computer or walking up to a board. That said, remember to timebox. After a point too much detail is unnecessary at this stage. Try to cover all the aspects mentioned at the start of this post, not in that order but activity by activity. An important piece that you can end the interview with, is asking about the challenges faced on the project. You will get insights that you might not gain by first-hand observation. If you have done a few interviews already, use further interviews to validate some of the points mentioned by others to get different viewpoints on the same thing. That too can be quite revealing at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Interview documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scribbling on a notepad may not feel like an overhead but cleaning up your notes to put in a Word document or a wiki page might seem tiresome. But you will thank yourself later for doing so. I am surprised how often I can&amp;#39;t read my own handwriting just a few days later. Also, searching for something specific in a physical notepad is not as quick as one might imagine. Typing out the notes electronically is also an opportunity to structure the observations better. This is when you can collate information in a role-specific manner rather than as individual interviews. You may start to see patterns. These will feed into the later phases of assessment, ie, highlighting bottlenecks and challenges, and making recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Here is a &lt;a href="/assets/media/docs/sample-assessment-interview-notes.pdf"&gt;sample document&lt;/a&gt;. And below are links on related skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mindtools.com/CommSkll/ActiveListening.htm"&gt;Active listening skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.skillsyouneed.com/ips/active-listening.html"&gt;Active listening signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.skillsyouneed.com/ips/questioning.html"&gt;Questioning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pagilista.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/wait-crucial-consulting-advice.html"&gt;W.A.I.T.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Coaching Engagements</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/agile-coaching-engagements</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-12</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Agile consulting, there can be different types of engagements that you get into with your client. One type of engagement may lead to another type. As an Agile Coach, you will find yourself participating across the board. Your focus areas will change based on what the engagement objectives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the typical types of engagements I have encountered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Assessments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a team, a department, or an organization simply is not aware of where they stand with respect to Agile adoption. They need answers to questions like: &amp;quot;Will they benefit from Agile Coaching, or are there too many prerequisites missing? Tentatively for how long will they need coaching before achieving self-sustenance? What areas need the most focus on?&amp;quot; Answering such questions means at least 2-3 days of work, involving interviews, discovery workshops, first-hand observations, metrics collections, etc. This is then followed by summarization and recommendation in the form of an assessment report, which typically contains a proposed coaching plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Pilot / Proof of Concept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Agile initiatives at an organization level, a department could have doubts about whether or not Agile would work for their specific context. In such cases, people agree to a Proof of Concept or Pilot, starting off with Agile Coaching with one selected team for a given duration of time, having a limited set of objectives. If the Pilot goes well, the department may agree to an overall Agile adoption. Coaches involved in a Pilot have to remain very conscious of how their time is spent, what activities they take up, and what focus areas to target, all the while keeping an eye out on measuring and showcasing benefits, even if small. Periodically they will send out progress reports, and finally wrap up the engagement with a summarization that highlights what worked and what did not work, challenges faced, and recommendations to overcome them. It is important to remind clients of what was decidedly out of scope. A Pilot could be anywhere between 2-8 weeks depending on the scope of objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Agile Adoption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile Adoption primarily refers to teams picking up Agile practices and using them for productivity gains and quality improvements. These practices could be process related such as time-boxed iterations, iteration planning, estimation, stand ups, and so on. Or these could be engineering related such as Test-driven Development, Refactoring, Continuous Integration, functional test automation, etc. However, it is established in most circles that Agile is more of a mindset than a set of processes and practices. That said, the latter helps teams try out well-described techniques that may be new to them, and possibly with time and guidance, they are able to see the short-term and long-term benefits behind the practices. Once teams reach this competency level, they are better placed to recognize and embrace the mindset change. This is what the Agile Coach will focus on: helping teams adopt certain practices, and gain higher skill levels in those, while also gradually guiding them towards the reasoning and benefits behind the practices. Tracking the team&amp;#39;s progress, checking for any drop in adoption after an initial spike, and continued efforts at sustenance, are also some of the key areas an Agile Coach looks into. Agile Adoption generally takes time, with some factors being team size, project complexity, and attitude and capabilities of team members. An Agile Coach will typically end up coaching multiple teams. Such an engagement can easily range from 2 months to a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Agile Transformation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had success with Agile Adoption, an organization may chose to embrace Agile completely across all of its departments and teams. This is Agile Transformation. It is typically organization-wide, spread horizontally as well as vertically. The focus shifts very visibly from processes and practices to mindset and culture. For it to be successful, common vision and buy-in are needed from all levels in the organization and across all departments. This will even include aspects such as IT policies, Recruitment, Performance Reviews, etc. An Agile consultant will end up focusing almost solely on strategic discussion and planning, with a lot of support from continued tactical coaching, either internal or external, at team levels. Such engagements are seen less frequently and are definitely long-term, easily spanning more than a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
For a further exploration of such topics, you can consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-adoption-transformation"&gt;Michael Sahota&amp;#39;s book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.agilealliance.org/programs/supporting-agile-adoption-it-is-about-change/"&gt;Agile Alliance documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/tags/agile%20adoption.html"&gt;Martin Fowler&amp;#39;s bliki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
