<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Aman King</title>
    <link>http://www.amanking.com</link>
    <pubDate>2013-12-15 17:26:08 +0530</pubDate>
    <item>
      <title>Assessment Interviews</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/assessment-interviews</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-13</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;During the assessment week of an &lt;a href="/agile-coaching-engagements"&gt;Agile coaching engagement&lt;/a&gt;, the goal is to learn about the current state of the team. Special attention is needed towards capturing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day-to-day activities of various roles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Additional activities such as on planning day, deployment day, etc&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools used to support these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Processes around these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interaction, collaboration, and dependency on other roles or teams during these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infrastructure environments involved in these activities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcome of these activities in an iteration-level view&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Challenges faced in performing any of these activities or the role in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to remain objective while making observations, and to not fall into the temptation of drawing conclusions or making recommendations. The latter is needed but should come towards the end of the assessment when holistic information is available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to get visibility into the above aspects is conducting interviews of team members. We need not talk to everyone but only a representative sample (perhaps 1-2 individuals) from each role. This should be complemented with first-hand observation of how they work. Here is a suggestion of how you could go about this activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Interview preparation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inform the Project Manager or equivalent a day or two in advance about the interviews you are planning to do. Learn about the various roles in the team, and ask the PM to inform team members to make time for the interview, which could last anywhere between 30 mins to an hour. It is usually a good idea to not conduct the interviews in a meeting room but at the desk of the individual. You should set up a time beforehand so that the interviewee is not distracted during the interview. Based on any insights already shared with you about the team&amp;#39;s current context, make a list of areas you want to specifically ask about. Some of these will be role-specific, and some general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Interview kickoff&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Introduce or re-introduce yourself to the individual. Briefly let them know why you are there with the team. Explain what the interview is about and how it will help. The interviewee should not feel like this is a test which has right or wrong answers. Thank the person for agreeing to the interview. Try to keep the interaction balanced between formal and informal so that it seems important and yet the interviewee feels comfortable in opening up and being forthright. Keep a notebook handy, and inform the interviewee that you&amp;#39;ll be scribbling notes during the interview, which you can share later after some clean-up if the interviewee is interested. It helps to reinforce transparency. First thing to note down is the person&amp;#39;s name and role, along with the interview date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Interview questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start simple by asking about the person&amp;#39;s background in brief, typically around industry experience, how long with the current team, and role description. Follow this up by asking the person to describe their &lt;em&gt;typical day&lt;/em&gt;. You can expect to get a lot of information out of this. Be ready to probe for details as and when required. Don&amp;#39;t stick to going breadth-wise or depth-wise; switch how you elicit details based on how relevant you feel a topic is. You can even ask the individual to &lt;em&gt;show-and-tell&lt;/em&gt; some aspects, perhaps by using a computer or walking up to a board. That said, remember to timebox. After a point too much detail is unnecessary at this stage. Try to cover all the aspects mentioned at the start of this post, not in that order but activity by activity. An important piece that you can end the interview with, is asking about the challenges faced on the project. You will get insights that you might not gain by first-hand observation. If you have done a few interviews already, use further interviews to validate some of the points mentioned by others to get different viewpoints on the same thing. That too can be quite revealing at times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Interview documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scribbling on a notepad may not feel like an overhead but cleaning up your notes to put in a Word document or a wiki page might seem tiresome. But you will thank yourself later for doing so. I am surprised how often I can&amp;#39;t read my own handwriting just a few days later. Also, searching for something specific in a physical notepad is not as quick as one might imagine. Typing out the notes electronically is also an opportunity to structure the observations better. This is when you can collate information in a role-specific manner rather than as individual interviews. You may start to see patterns. These will feed into the later phases of assessment, ie, highlighting bottlenecks and challenges, and making recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Here is a &lt;a href="/assets/media/docs/sample-assessment-interview-notes.pdf"&gt;sample document&lt;/a&gt;. And below are links on related skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mindtools.com/CommSkll/ActiveListening.htm"&gt;Active listening skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.skillsyouneed.com/ips/active-listening.html"&gt;Active listening signs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.skillsyouneed.com/ips/questioning.html"&gt;Questioning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pagilista.blogspot.co.uk/2012/04/wait-crucial-consulting-advice.html"&gt;W.A.I.T.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Coaching Engagements</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/agile-coaching-engagements</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-12</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Agile consulting, there can be different types of engagements that you get into with your client. One type of engagement may lead to another type. As an Agile Coach, you will find yourself participating across the board. Your focus areas will change based on what the engagement objectives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the typical types of engagements I have encountered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Assessments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a team, a department, or an organization simply is not aware of where they stand with respect to Agile adoption. They need answers to questions like: &amp;quot;Will they benefit from Agile Coaching, or are there too many prerequisites missing? Tentatively for how long will they need coaching before achieving self-sustenance? What areas need the most focus on?&amp;quot; Answering such questions means at least 2-3 days of work, involving interviews, discovery workshops, first-hand observations, metrics collections, etc. This is then followed by summarization and recommendation in the form of an assessment report, which typically contains a proposed coaching plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Pilot / Proof of Concept&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Agile initiatives at an organization level, a department could have doubts about whether or not Agile would work for their specific context. In such cases, people agree to a Proof of Concept or Pilot, starting off with Agile Coaching with one selected team for a given duration of time, having a limited set of objectives. If the Pilot goes well, the department may agree to an overall Agile adoption. Coaches involved in a Pilot have to remain very conscious of how their time is spent, what activities they take up, and what focus areas to target, all the while keeping an eye out on measuring and showcasing benefits, even if small. Periodically they will send out progress reports, and finally wrap up the engagement with a summarization that highlights what worked and what did not work, challenges faced, and recommendations to overcome them. It is important to remind clients of what was decidedly out of scope. A Pilot could be anywhere between 2-8 weeks depending on the scope of objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Agile Adoption&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile Adoption primarily refers to teams picking up Agile practices and using them for productivity gains and quality improvements. These practices could be process related such as time-boxed iterations, iteration planning, estimation, stand ups, and so on. Or these could be engineering related such as Test-driven Development, Refactoring, Continuous Integration, functional test automation, etc. However, it is established in most circles that Agile is more of a mindset than a set of processes and practices. That said, the latter helps teams try out well-described techniques that may be new to them, and possibly with time and guidance, they are able to see the short-term and long-term benefits behind the practices. Once teams reach this competency level, they are better placed to recognize and embrace the mindset change. This is what the Agile Coach will focus on: helping teams adopt certain practices, and gain higher skill levels in those, while also gradually guiding them towards the reasoning and benefits behind the practices. Tracking the team&amp;#39;s progress, checking for any drop in adoption after an initial spike, and continued efforts at sustenance, are also some of the key areas an Agile Coach looks into. Agile Adoption generally takes time, with some factors being team size, project complexity, and attitude and capabilities of team members. An Agile Coach will typically end up coaching multiple teams. Such an engagement can easily range from 2 months to a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_3"&gt;Agile Transformation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having had success with Agile Adoption, an organization may chose to embrace Agile completely across all of its departments and teams. This is Agile Transformation. It is typically organization-wide, spread horizontally as well as vertically. The focus shifts very visibly from processes and practices to mindset and culture. For it to be successful, common vision and buy-in are needed from all levels in the organization and across all departments. This will even include aspects such as IT policies, Recruitment, Performance Reviews, etc. An Agile consultant will end up focusing almost solely on strategic discussion and planning, with a lot of support from continued tactical coaching, either internal or external, at team levels. Such engagements are seen less frequently and are definitely long-term, easily spanning more than a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
For a further exploration of such topics, you can consider:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.infoq.com/minibooks/agile-adoption-transformation"&gt;Michael Sahota&amp;#39;s book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.agilealliance.org/programs/supporting-agile-adoption-it-is-about-change/"&gt;Agile Alliance documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/tags/agile%20adoption.html"&gt;Martin Fowler&amp;#39;s bliki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile Coaching Roles</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/agile-coaching-roles</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-11</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;To me, &lt;a href="/coaching-basics"&gt;Coaching&lt;/a&gt; is about getting the most out of individuals or teams by raising their awareness levels, about their current environment, about the environment outside theirs, and most important of all, about their own potential. This is done mostly by asking them the right questions, and not by providing them ready-made answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My definition of an &lt;em&gt;Agile Coach&lt;/em&gt;, on the other hand, is less restrictive. As an Agile Coach, coaching is my primary &lt;em&gt;modus operandi&lt;/em&gt;. But there are times when I make recommendations based on my practitioner background. I also complement coaching with aspects of mentoring and training. For example, relating personal experiences and sharing useful resources can increase someone&amp;#39;s curiosity and give them a clear direction. Conducting a workshop can help kickstart a group on practices like TDD and Refactoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even within the scope of Agile Coaching, I have been exposed to a variety of roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_0"&gt;Role-based Practices Coaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An Agile Coach helps team members understand their roles in an Agile setting. This involves skills-building. You may join a team as a single cross-skilled coach or as a trio of role-specific coaches: a Tech Coach, a QA Coach, and a BA Coach. With Developers, a coach will pair actively to spread practices like TDD, Refactoring, CI, etc, and will run workshops and brown bag sessions. With Testers, a coach could cover creating test scenarios from acceptance criteria, automated testing, test pyramid, and so on. For Business Analysts or Product Owners, the focus will be on prioritization exercises, negotiation skills, story writing, story slicing, determining NFRs, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_1"&gt;Process Coaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While focusing on role-specific skills and practices is important, some teams may need help in determining what process works for them, adapting them over time, and so on. This could involve defining how each role contributes to the process, and also in general, how the entire team collaborates and focuses on improvement. Having effective stand ups, planning meetings, demos, and retrospectives fall under this. Other aspects could involve helping the team determine some metrics to observe and improve. Eg: pairing matrix, confidence meter, build failures in a day, velocity, cycle time, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="toc_2"&gt;Leadership Coaching&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At times, it is not only team members who need coaching, but their leadership as well. These may include the Team Lead, the Project Manager, the Architect Head, the Programme Manager, the Department Head, and so on. The conversation topics are usually broader level and strategic, such as prioritization of teams for Agile adoption, facilitating empowered teams, investing in appropriate infrastructure or continuous delivery initiatives, reducing overhead in IT policies, identifying improvements in architecture and ecosystem, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In most cases, a single Agile Coach on an engagement will touch upon all of the above but to varying degrees. It will be a factor of the company culture, need of the hour, and personal motivations of the people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following provide further insights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.agilecoachinginstitute.com/agile-competency-whitepaper/"&gt;Agile Coaching Competencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://blogs.agilefaqs.com/2013/07/21/how-coaching-is-different-from-training-mentoring-counseling-and-consulting"&gt;Comparison of Coaching, Training, Mentoring, Consulting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Coaching-Agile-Teams-ScrumMasters-Addison-Wesley-ebook/dp/B003QP47YG/"&gt;Coaching Agile Teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coaching Basics</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/coaching-basics</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-10</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;em&gt;Coaching&lt;/em&gt; is overloaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparatively, terms like &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.refactoring.com/"&gt;Refactoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?YouArentGonnaNeedIt"&gt;YAGNI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; are recently invented. But despite having had clear definitions to start with, these words still suffer from &lt;a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/RefactoringMalapropism.html"&gt;malapropism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Coaching&lt;/em&gt; is a plain English word, around since ages. It is not surprising that its definition in the professional world remains open. This is evident from its &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coaching"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there have been attempts to describe coaching better, acknowledging the wide spectrum it could cover, and yet putting some boundaries to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal view on the term is still evolving despite having played the Agile Coach role. So far I&amp;#39;ve kept it simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coaching is not classroom training; it is interpersonal; it creates awareness in individuals and teams; it is more about asking than telling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check these links for less &lt;em&gt;fuzzy&lt;/em&gt; definitions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.abdn.ac.uk/mgtskills/people/people2/people2-4/"&gt;Key elements of coaching&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://tle.tafevc.com.au/toolbox/file/44cc9067-a0f9-5e24-d9c7-67a5678d4aa9/1/10_04a.zip/toolbox/resources/res1050/res1050.htm"&gt;Coaching styles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.coachville.com/home/html/coaching_basics"&gt;Coaching skills&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agile India 2014</title>
      <link>http://www.amanking.com/agile-india-2014</link>
      <pubDate>2013-12-09</pubDate>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2014.agileindia.org/"&gt;Agile India 2014&lt;/a&gt; is scheduled for 26th Feb - 1st Mar 2014 in Bangalore. My talk, &lt;a href="http://present.agileindia.org/proposal/16/from-practitioner-to-coach"&gt;From Practitioner to Coach&lt;/a&gt;, has been selected for the conference under the Scaling Agile track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In support of the presentation, I will blog about various coaching-related topics here. Most of the posts will be short, and will be tagged as a &lt;em&gt;nugget&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m looking forward to the conference! It has an excellent line up of speakers and topics. Do check it out yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2014.agileindia.org/" target="_blank" title="I am speaking at Agile India 2014"&gt;&lt;img src="/assets/media/images/badges/speaker-agile-india-2014.png" title="I am speaking at Agile India 2014" alt="I am speaking at Agile India 2014"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
